What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at some
of the latest research
on leaky gut syndrome.
Did you know that
common drugs, foods,
and beverages can disrupt the
integrity of our intestinal barrier?
Here’s the story.
Intestinal permeability,
the leakiness of our gut,
may be a new target for
disease prevention and therapy.
With all its little folds, our
intestinal barrier covers a surface
of more than 4,000 square feet —
that's bigger than a tennis
court — and requires
approximately 40% of our body's
total energy expenditure to maintain.
Mounting evidence implicates the
disruption of intestinal barrier
integrity in the development
of numerous ailments
such as inflammatory bowel disease.
Here, researchers measured intestinal
permeability using blue food coloring.
It stays in your gut if you're healthy,
but can be detected in the blood
of extremely sick individuals as
their gut barrier breaks down.
You don't have to end up in the ICU
to develop a leaky gut though.
Simply taking some aspirin
or ibuprofen can do the trick.
Indeed, taking two regular aspirin,
or two extra-strength aspirin just once
can increase the leakiness of
your gut. These results suggest
even healthy individuals should
be cautious with aspirin use
as it may result in
gastrointestinal barrier dysfunction.
What about buffered aspirin?
It doesn't make any difference:
both regular aspirin and Bufferin
produced multiple erosions
in the inner lining of the
stomach and intestines.
Put a scope down people's throats
and you can see extensive erosions
and redness inside 90% of people
taking aspirin or Bufferin
in their recommended doses.
How many hours does it take
for the damage to occur?
None. It happens within 5 minutes.
Acetaminophen, sold as Tylenol
in the U.S., would be a better choice,
unless you have problems
with your liver.
And rather than making things better,
Vitamin C supplements appeared
to make the aspirin-induced increase
in gut leakiness even worse.
Interestingly, this may be why NSAID
drugs like aspirin, ibuprofen,
and naproxen
are involved in up to 25% of
food-induced anaphylaxis;
in other words, increasing the odds
of life-threatening food allergy attacks
by more than 10-fold,
presumably because these drugs
increase the leakiness
of the intestinal barrier,
causing tiny food particles
to slip into the bloodstream.
Okay, but why can exercise
increase risk, too?
Strenuous exercise, like an hour
at 70% of maximum capacity,
can divert so much blood to the muscles,
away from your internal organs
that it can cause transient
injury to your intestines,
causing mild gut leakiness.
But this can be aggravated
if athletes take ibuprofen
or any of the other NSAID drugs,
which is unfortunately all too common.
Alcohol can also be a risk factor
for food allergy attacks for
the same reason:
increasing gut leakiness.
But cut out the alcohol
and your gut can heal up.
What other dietary components
can make a difference?
Elevated consumption of saturated fat,
which is found in meat, dairy, and junk,
can cause the growth of bad bacteria,
which make the rotten egg gas
hydrogen sulfide, which can
degrade the protective mucus layer.
It is said to be clear that high fat diets,
in general, negatively impact
intestinal health by disrupting
the intestinal barrier system
through a variety of mechanisms.
But most of the vast array of studies
cited on the negative effects
of high-fat diet on gut leakiness
were done on lab animals
or in a petri dish.
You don't know for sure
until you put it to the test.
Rates of obesity and other
cardiometabolic disorders
have increased rapidly in parallel
with a transition from traditional
lower-fat diets to higher-fat diets.
We know a disturbance in our good gut
flora has been shown to be associated
with a high risk of many
of these same diseases.
And studies using rodents
suggest that a high-fat diet
unbalances the microbiome and impairs
the gut barrier, resulting in disease.
To connect all the dots, though, we
need a human interventional trial,
and here we go: a 6-month
randomized controlled-feeding trial
on the effects of dietary
fat on gut microbiota.
And indeed, higher fat consumption
appeared to be associated
with unfavorable changes
in the gut microbiome, and
proinflammatory factors in the blood.
And note: this wasn't meat and dairy.
The researchers just swapped in
refined carbs in place of refined fats,
like white rice and white flour for oil.
These findings suggest countries
westernizing their diets
should advise against increasing
intakes of dietary fat,
while countries that have already
adopted westernized diets
should consider cutting down.
So far, we've discussed things
to prevent a leaky gut.
What about foods to heal a leaky gut?
That's what we'll cover next.
Our intestinal tract is the largest barrier
between us and the environment.
More than what we touch or breathe,
what we eat is our largest exposure to
the outside world. Normally, our entire
gastro-intestinal tract is impervious
to what is inside of it, allowing
our body to pick and choose
what comes in or out.
But there are things that may make
our gut leaky, and chief among them
is our diet. What happens is
the Standard American Diet
can cause gut dysbiosis, meaning
a disruption in our gut microbiome,
which can lead to intestinal inflammation
and a leaky intestinal barrier.
Then tiny bits of undigested
food, microbes, and toxins
can slip uninvited through our
gut lining into our bloodstream
and trigger chronic
systemic inflammation.
To avoid this dysbiosis and
intestinal inflammation,
plants should be preferred.
Vegetarian diet gut bacteria
are associated with
intestinal microbiome balance,
high bacterial biodiversity, and
integrity of the intestinal barrier.
They tend to suffer from
markedly fewer uremic toxins,
like indole and p-cresol,
and because fiber is the primary
food for our gut microbiome,
the gut bacteria of those
eating plant-based diets
produce more of the good stuff,
the short-chain fatty acids
that fulfill a protective and
nourishing role for the cells lining
our gut, ensuring the preservation
of the intestinal barrier.
Plant fiber is of prime
importance to the preservation
of the intestinal barrier integrity,
but you can't know for sure
until you put it to the test.
People were given whole grains,
beans and lentils, fruits, vegetables,
and nuts and seeds, and got a
significant reduction in zonulin levels.
Zonulin is a protein responsible
for the disassembling
of the tight junctions between gut
lining cells, and so it's a biomarker
that reflects an impairment
of the intestinal barrier.
In other words, zonulin is considered
to be a useful marker of a leaky gut.
But since adding all those plants
seemed to lower levels, that may
imply that appropriate fiber intake
helps to maintain the proper structure
and function of the intestinal barrier.
But whole healthy plant foods
have a lot more than fiber.
How do we know it's the fiber?
And the study didn't even
have a control group.
That's why they say gut permeability
might be improved by dietary fiber.
To prove cause-and-effect, it'd be nice
to have a randomized double-blind
crossover study where you
compare the effect of the same food
with or without fiber,
and here we go.
People were randomized to pasta,
with or without added fiber,
and there was a significant
drop in zonulin levels
in the added fiber group,
so fiber does appear
to improve gut leakiness.
Any plant foods in particular
that may help?
Curcumin, the yellow pigment
in the spice turmeric,
can help prevent the intestinal
damage done by ibuprofen-type
drugs, but that's in rats.
Similar protection was noted for
the broccoli compound sulforaphane,
but that was in mice.
No human studies on broccoli yet,
but there was a study on three
days of the equivalent of about
2 to 3 teaspoons a day of turmeric,
which did reduce the gastrointestinal
barrier damage caused by exercise.
Less may work, too, but no smaller
doses have been put to the test.
If you ask alternative
medicine practitioners
what treatments they
use for a leaky gut,
#1 on the list, after reducing
alcohol consumption, is zinc.
Zinc doesn't just protect against
aspirin-like drug-induced damage in rats.
When put to the test in
a randomized trial of humans,
the same thing was found.
The NSAID drug indomethacin caused
a three-fold rise in gut permeability
as one would expect
from that class of drugs,
but when they were also taking zinc,
this prevented the rise in permeability,
strongly suggesting a small
intestinal protective effect.
The dose they used was
massive though: 75 mg a day;
that's nearly twice the tolerable
upper daily limit for zinc.
What about getting zinc
just at regular food doses?
There was a significant improvement
in gut leakiness even with a dose
of just three milligrams of zinc,
suggesting that even relatively low
zinc supplementation may work.
You can get the three
extra milligrams of zinc
in your daily diet
eating a cup of cooked lentils.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.